PROFESSOR: OK, today we're going to
be talking about Markov decision
processes, which are a way of
formalizing the idea of
non-deterministic search, which
is search when your action's
outcomes are uncertain.
Why would we be unsure what the outcome
of our actions is going to be?
Well, maybe we've got a robot on
a ledge, and we take the action
to cross the ledge.
What's going to happen?
Well, maybe we'll cross the ledge.
Maybe we'll fall into the fire pit.
We're not really sure.
We can commit to the action, but of
course the outcome isn't entirely
under our control.
That's going to happen in general.
There's just all kinds of times
where you take some action--
maybe, you're a can opener robot.
And you take the can and you open it.
And what's underneath?
More can, right?
So let's try to formalize this.
Our running example is going
to be this grid world.
You're going to see this as
well on your projects.
So grid world is a maze-like problem.
You've got an agent living in a grid,
just like we did for project one.
There are going to be walls that
block the agent's path.
And then there are going
to various rewards.
The tricky thing is going to be that the
actions of the agent can now fail,
and in particular, movement
is going to be noisy.
So if I take an action--
for example, north is an action--
I can attempt to go north.
It doesn't mean that I actually will.
In this particular instance of grid
world, 80% of the time, the action you
take has the expected result.
For example, the action north actually
moves you 1 square to the north.
10% of the time, however, an action
will take you clockwise--
and then 10% of the time,
counterclockwise--
from the intended direction.
So in this particular case, if I try
to go north, 80% chance of going
north, but I've also got a 10% chance
of going west and a 10% chance of
going east.
If for any reason there's a wall in
the way of the direction this rule
would take you, you stay put.
Like I said, there are rewards in this
maze, and the whole point is to gather
the rewards.
There are two kinds of rewards
in the grid world.
One are the terminal utilities.
And here these are shown as plus
1 and minus 1, and they're
visualized here as a gem.
That's a plus 1.
If you get to that gem and you take the
action "exit," the game ends and
you get a plus 1.
The red fire pit is shown
as a minus 1.
If you get into that square, you
take the action "exit," and you
receive a minus 1.
There's another kind of reward in grid
world, which is every step you take
comes along with a little tiny reward.
And this is sometimes called a living
reward or a living penalty, based on
whether it's positive or negative.
And if it's positive, well, you
walk around and get happier.
If it's negative, then it costs a little
bit of pain every step, and you
want things to end quickly.
The big rewards are, in general,
going to be at the end.
So what should the agents goal be?
Well, the simplest goal and the one
we'll take for now is the agent should
maximize the sum of its rewards.
In general, that's going to involve
getting to a big reward and taking it.
If this were deterministic search in
a normal maze, this is what your
successor function and your
actions would do, right?
You're in some state, you take the
action north, and the result of that
is you are now one square
to the north.
In grid world, because it's noisy, you
can still take the action north, but
now you're not sure what the
result's going to be.
So in this particular case, when
the agent tries to go north,
maybe it goes north.
In fact, that's the 80%
outcome in this case.
But there's a 10% chance of going
to the left or the right.
And if you end up going to
the right, that's OK.
If you end up going to the
left, that's pretty bad.
And so when you plan, you're
going to have to take these
outcomes into account.
Formally speaking, this
kind of problem--
grid world in this case--
is a Markov decision process.
A Markov decision process is a
lot like a search problem.
It's got a set of states,
just like search did.
And it's kind of got a successor
function like search did.
Unlike in search, we're going to take
the successor function and break it
into a few pieces.
We're going to have an idea of actions,
which are the actions you
take, like north, south,
east, or west.
We're then going to have
a transition function.
And this notation is important because
we're going to see it over and over
again in the next few lectures.
So let's look at the transition
function.
The transition function here we
write T of s, a, s-prime.
What is that?
You are in some states s.
You take some action a.
s-prime is a possible result.
The function T(s, a, s-prime) tells
you how likely that result is.
And in that sense, it's a
conditional probability.
So when you see the transition function,
you think, oh, that's the
probability that I end up in s-prime,
if from state s I take action a.
This is called the transition
function.
It's also sometimes called the model,
because it's your way of representing
what actually happens in the world,
and sometimes called the dynamics,
because it represents how the world
evolves in response to your actions.
This transition function is basically
the successor function.
The difference is now there are lots of
different s-primes that can happen.
And they all have various
probabilities, T,
associated with them.
Also very much like search, but slightly
different, is this idea of a
reward function.
The reward function is R of s, a,
s-prime, meaning you get a reward that
depends on the state you were in, the
action you took, and the outcome.
You might not know your actual reward
until you see whether or not you fell
into the pit.
In some formulations, R will only
depend on s or s-prime.
What's this?
This is basically the cost function from
search, except in search, we want
the cost to be small.
In the case of MDPs, in general,
we want the rewards to be big.
Of course, we've also got this
idea of a start state.
We might have a terminal state.
Here's another important difference
between MDPs and search problems,
because MDPs very often go on forever.
And we'll see an example of that soon.
So what are MDPs?
They're non-deterministic
search problems.
They're basically taking search that
we know and love and adding the
necessary machinery to support
the idea that actions can
have multiple outcomes.
In fact, this is the class of problems
that Expectimax search solved.
We'll actually get a new tool very soon
that can solve them in sometimes
a better way than Expectimax.
But to a first approximation, when you
see an MDP, you think, oh, that's a
lot like what Expectimax did.
I have a choices at a state, but then
my actions have uncertain outcomes.
Let's take a look at grid world
actually happening.
So here's grid world.
For now, ignore the numbers.
They'll become important later.
And you can also watch down here at
the bottom, which is going to echo
what I press.
So what I'm going to try to do is I'm
going to try to get the agent, which
here is the blue dot, into the good
reward square, which is up here.
Remember, there's a plus 1 there.
And I'm going to walk it step by step.
And I'm going to go to
the right and up.
You won't be able to see what I press
except when it echoes below.
The important thing is usually
the key I press happens.
But sometimes the agent slips.
So I'm going to press east.
And look, you can see I took
the action east, but I
ended up where I started.
I'm going to take it again.
I went east.
I'm going to try east again.
It worked.
I'm going to try north.
Now this is a little tricky, because if
you think about this square here,
I'm taking a little bit of a risk.
Because this lower exit here
is actually a pit.
Hopefully I won't fall into it.
90% chance.
It worked out.
I'm going to go east again
and that succeeded.
I end up in this square.
Now in the exact formulation of grid
world here that we have, when you get
into one of these exit squares,
you're not done yet.
You don't receive your reward yet.
You have to take a special action.
It's the only action you can take.
It's called exit.
And so now I'll be forced to take
the exit action, and I will
receive my plus 1.
And if I scroll through the rewards,
you'll see I got a bunch of little
negative 0.1's.
That was the living reward, or in
this case, a living penalty.
And then at the very end, I
ended in the exit state.
I took the action to exit,
and I got a reward of 1.
That's how it works in grid world.
OK, Markov decision problems.
Who's this Markov guy and what's
he doing in my search problem?
In general in this course, Markov
is going to mean the same thing.
It's going to mean that, given the
present state, the future and the past
are independent in the
appropriate way.
For a Markov decision process, what that
specifically means is that the
probability distribution over your
outcomes depends only on the current
state and action, not on the whole
history of how you got there.
This is actually just like search.
If you remember, for search, we had to
make sure our state was appropriate
such that the successor function only
depended on the state and not the
history of how I got there.
And so sometimes we had to encode things
into our state like which food
pellets were left and so on, in
order to get that property.
An important property in an MDP is
to make sure that you define your
transition function and your state
in such a way that the transition
probabilities depend only on the
current state and action.
If we remember back to single-agent
search problems, what did we do?
We input a problem.
Some solution method like
A star search ran.
And the output was a plan.
The plan was a sequence of actions
to transform the start
state into a goal state.
That's not going to work here, because
for example, if you remember, when I
was doing the grid world by hand, that
first step I tried to go east, but it
didn't happen.
So if I just blindly executed east,
east, east, north, north,
north, east, exit--
well, it wouldn't have
worked in that case.
And in general, I'm not going to know
what sequence of actions to take,
because I don't know what those
actions are going to do.
The relevant idea is not a
plan now but a policy.
And what a policy is, is a mapping
from states to actions.
And it tells me in each state
what action to take.
So actually, you can see here
in the illustration--
you can see an example of a policy for
that same grid world that in every
state tells you what to do.
So it might tell you to go north.
It might tell you to go east.
If you end up trying to go east and
you end up in the state where you
started, it just tells you, go east
again, because that's what you do in
that state.
So a policy gives an action
for each state.
An optimal policy is the one that
maximizes the agent's expected utility
if followed.
So there are good policies
and bad policies.
We're going to want to be able
to find the best ones, which
are the optimal policies.
If we actually wrote the policy out
explicitly, meaning we wrote down for
every single state what to do--
like what's shown here on the map--
then in fact this defines
a reflex agent.
You look at your state,
you do your action.
No more thinking is required.
All the thinking went into coming
up with the policy.
Now Expectimax didn't really compute
an explicit policy in this sense.
What Expectimax did for these kinds of
problems is, from a given state, it
did a forward-thinking computation that
produced one entry of the policy,
which you then took.
And wherever you landed, you
ran Expectimax again.
So on one hand, Expectimax is a
way of solving these problems.
And on the other hand, it doesn't
compute an explicit policy.
That can be a good thing
or a bad thing.
It can be bad because you might have
to redo a lot of work if you keep
ending up in the same states.
It can be good because sometimes you
have so many states you couldn't write
down an explicit policy anyway.
Let's see some optimal policies.
These are all instances of grid world.
They all have a plus
1 and minus 1 exit.
Where they differ is the reward
you receive on every step.
So what's shown here is the optimal
policy if the living reward--
in this case, living penalty--
is very, very mild.
So there's not a lot of pressure
to hurry up and end the game.
So let's look and see what
this policy does.
Well, mostly it's pretty
interpretable.
For example, from here, we're
going to go up and around.
Let's see what else it does.
Well, it kind of does this funny
thing in this square here.
What's it doing there?
It's going into the wall.
Why does it go into the wall?
This is an example of, we feed the rules
of the game in, we compute the
optimal behavior, and maybe--
like that AIBO that likes to poop the
soccer ball out in order to shoot--
sometimes the behavior isn't what we
expected, but it's still optimal.
So in this case, what
is this position?
Essentially you've got this
pit right behind you.
You really, really do not want
to fall into the pit.
Rather than trying to move north or
south, you move into the wall.
What can happen?
Well, you're probably
going to stay put.
That's not too bad, because the
living penalty is small.
But you might go north or south,
both of which are safe.
If you did anything else,
you would risk the pit.
So in fact, this is the agent pressing
its chest against the wall and just
waiting, waiting, waiting,
until it gets out of this
scary situation safely.
This agent is very conservative,
because each
timestep costs very little.
All right.
What happens if we make this
living penalty more severe?
So we're putting a little bit of
pressure on the agent, that if it just
wanders around, it starts
losing points.
Well, here now it's minus 0.03.
And you can see it's still the case
that we go around to the exit.
Something that's changed here is from
that scary position we now go straight
towards the exit, and we risk the pit,
because that small chance of falling
into the pit is not worth the time it's
going to take to shimmy our way
out by trying to bang into the wall.
However life is still cheap enough that
we go the long way around from
the bottom squares.
What happens if we make the
living reward even worse?
Well, again, from some squares we
head towards the positive exit.
But now we're willing to
take the shortcut.
We're not going to take
the long way around.
Yes, the shortcut risks the pit.
What happens if we make the living
reward extremely severe?
What happens if we make it minus 2?
It costs you minus 2 every step
regardless, of what you do?
What do you want to do?
You want to end the game, which
means straight into the exit.
Any exit will do.
The pit looks bad, but it's
not as bad as moving.
So you get a slightly depressed agent
when the living rewards are negative.
And maybe that's not surprising,
given what we've input
as a utility function.
OK.
So this is another example of, we input
the utilities and the behavior
emerges from a unified computation.